Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): [Mev'iza-i belige] Title (English): [Eloquent sermon] Alternative titles: [????? ?????, Mawi?ah-i balighah][, Date: [16--?]; Manuscript number: 274; 88 leaves: paper; 145 x 94 mm. bound to 148 x 100 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Marbled paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over the spine, and marble paste- downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; 1b illuminated. (Box 63)
  The name of the author appears as Cemaleddin Halvetî on 1b, but self-references in the text only occur as Cemali. If correctly identified, he is also known as Çelebi Halife. See Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 80- 81.
  Treatise on Sufism.
- Title (Romanized): [el-]Cevherü'l-ferid fi't-t?bbi'l-cedid Title (English): The unique jewel in modern medicine Alternative titles: ?????? ?????? ?? ???? ??????, al-jawhar al-farid fi ?ib al- jadid, Date: 1718; Manuscript number: 275; 169 leaves: paper; 145 x 94 mm. bound to 148 x 100 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faux brown Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 63)
  In the manuscript, the author refers to himself as Ömer Sehrî. See Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. III: 228-9, where the full name is spelled Ömer Sifai b. Seyh Hasan Efendi
  Treatise on medicine and pharmacology, originally composed in July 1700 in Damascus (169a)
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Gülsen-i raz Title (English): [translation of] the flower-garden of mystery Alternative titles: ???? ???, Gulshan-i raz, Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 276; 136 leaves: paper; 171 x 123 mm. bound to 171 x 123 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather with gilt decoration and pink paste-downs; back cover torn off. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 63)
  A Turkish translation of the Sufi poem in Persian by Shabistari (Ma?mud ibn Abd al-Karim, d. ca. 1320), originally composed in 1425 (6b).
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i Milel ve nihal Title (English): Translations of nations and faiths Alternative titles: ????? ??? ? ???, Date: Before 1824; Manuscript number: 277; 121 leaves: paper; 195 x 113 mm. bound to 195 x 116 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather with gilt decoration, fore-edge flap, and orange paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b decorated with gold color. (Box 63)
  A treatise on various Islamic sects, being a translation of an Arabic original entitled al-Milal wa-al-ni?al by Abd al- Karim Shahrastani (1086?-1153).
- Title (Romanized): Bedayiü'z-zuhûr fî vekayi'i'd-duhûr Title (English): Astonishing glows regarding the occurences of the ages Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ?? ????? ??????, Bada'í al-zuhur fi waqa'í al-duhur, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 278; 234 leaves: paper; 208 x 136 mm. bound to 206 x 136 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with pink paste-downs; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 64)
  The author may or may not be Rahîmî, Kütahyal?, 16th cent.
  Tales of prophets extracted and translated from an Arabic original entitled Bada'í al-zuhur fi waqa'í al-duhur by Ibn Iyas (1448-ca. 1524). The first forty leaves of the manuscript cover the creation of the universe. The tales of the prophets begin on 41b with the repetition of the poem that also opens 1b. A note in a later hand on 1a says that the author(?) had written the forty-third leaf in his own hand.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Kaside-i Bürde Title (English): [The translation of] the ode Burdah Alternative titles: ????? ????, Burdah, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 279; 98 leaves: paper; 208 x 136 mm. bound to 206 x 136 mm.; Layout: 18 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Marble paper on boards, with burgundy leather stripe over the spine, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia. (Box 64)
  See Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 384. The second title (Hadis-i Erba'in) is in verse, and at least two authors have been credited with such a composition with this title. These are Kemalpasazade (1468 or 9-1534) and Okcuzade Mehmet Sahî (d. 1629). See Karatay, F. E. Topkap? Saray? Müzesi Kütüphanesi türkce yazmalar katalogu, in the index under the title (2874 and 2979).
  A short poem on the praise of the prophet and his mysteries, being a translation of Burdah of al-Bu?iri. The manuscript contains two other titles.
- Title (Romanized): [Esmarü'l-hadaik] Uniform title: Esmar el-hadaik, Esmarü'l-hadayik Title (English): [Fruits of the garden] Alternative titles: [????? ???????], Athmar al-?ada'iq, Date: 1849; Manuscript number: 280; 25 leaves: paper; 200 x 128 mm. bound to 199 x 126 mm.; Layout: Average 18 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Blue cloth on boards, with gilt burgundy leather stripe around the edges, and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black, red, and blue ink, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b, 7b, and 18b illuminated.
  Geneological table of Ottoman Sultans and notables, originally composed in 1847 or 47, during the reign of Ottoman Sultan Abdülmecit (18391861).
- Title (Romanized): [Câmi'ü'l-fevaid] Title (English): [Anthology of useful things] Alternative titles: ???? ???????, ???? ???????, Jamí al-fawa'id, Date: 1660 September; Manuscript number: 281; 160 leaves: paper; 198 x 135 mm. bound to 198 x 137 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Decorated red paper on boards, with brown leather stripe around the edges, purple paste-downs, and fore-edge flap (torn off). Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 64)
  A book of Hadith translated into Turkish and divided into 16 chapters, covering such topics as faith, miracles, the virtues of the Koran, prayer, charity, etc. It may be a translation of the Arabic text entitled Jamí al-fawa'id min Jamí al-u?ul wa-Majmá al-zawa'id written by Rudani (Mu?ammad ibn Mu?ammad, 1627 or 8-1682 or 3). There are two very short treatises on dream interpretation and the Koran appended to the end.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i serh-i] Dürr-i yetim Title (English): [Translation of the commentary on] the Virgin pearl Alternative titles: ?? ????, al-Durr al-yatim, al-Mu?annaf, Date: 1720; Manuscript number: 282; 100 leaves: paper; 197 x 149 mm. bound to 200 x 150 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red leather, gilt around the edges, with brown leather stripe over spine, and red paste-downs; rebound in paper. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages and underlining in red. (Box 64)
  Turkish commentary and translation of an Arabic original on the science of Koranic recitation by Birgivî Mehmet Efendi, ca. 1522-1573. However, information in Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun as well as the phrase "Translation of the commentary of al-Rumi" on the paper cover suggest that the present translation is of the commentary written on Birgivî's work by a certain Ahmet Faiz Rumi and entitled "al-Mu?annaf".
- Title (Romanized): [Mürsidü's-salikîn] Title (English): [Guide of the wayfarers] Alternative titles: [???? ????????], Murshid al- salikin, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 283; 138 leaves: paper; 191 x 127 mm. bound to 183 x 126 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather, brittle. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage. (Box 64)
  Treatise on Sufism attributed to the founder of the Bayrami lodge.
- Title (Romanized): Tarih-i maarif Uniform title: Tarih-i Gülsen-i maârif Title (English): History of the known things Alternative titles: ????? ?????, Tarih-i Gülsen-i maârif, Tarih-i Gülsen-i Máarif, Tarikh-i gulshan-i máarif, Date: 1848; Manuscript number: 284; 208 leaves: paper; 174 x 124 mm. bound to 178 x 132 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green paper on boards, with green paste-downs, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 64)
  The author merely refers to himself as Said. His name also appears as: Saîd, Farâizizâde Mehmed and Sait, Mehmet (Harvard).
  A history of biblical/Koranic prophets, apparently part of a multi-volume ouvre.
- Title (Romanized): [Emrî Divan?] Title (English): [Poetic anthology of Emrî], Date: 1595 October; Manuscript number: 285; 59 leaves: paper; 190 x 117 mm. bound to 189 x 117 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Soft leather with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 64)
  Poetic anthology of the Ottoman poet Emrî.
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Durrat al-taj, Date: 1649 January; Manuscript number: 286; 218 leaves: paper; 197 x 135 mm. bound to 192 x 138 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green paper on boards, with gilt decoration, and brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b and 88b illuminated. (Box 64)
  Veysî's biography of the prophet Muhammad. The manuscript also contains some of the author's letters, as well as a short treatise by the Ottoman poet Nev'îzade (Ata'i, Ata Allah ibn Ya?ya, 17th cent.)
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Durrat al-taj, Date: 1639 July; Manuscript number: 287; 193 leaves: paper; 197 x 135 mm. bound to 192 x 138 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red velvet on boards, with gilt-decorated brown leather around the edges, fore-edge flap, and blue paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b and 102b illuminated. (Box 65)
- Title (Romanized): [Zeyl-i Nâbi] Uniform title: Zeyl-i Nâbi Title (English): [The continuation of Nâbi] Alternative titles: ??? ????, Dhayl-i Nabi, Date: 1724 February; Manuscript number: 288; 161 leaves: paper; 197 x 135 mm. bound to 192 x 138 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Red leather, blind-stamped, with printed gilt decoration. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 3b illuminated. (Box 65)
  The continuation of Veysî's biography of the prophet Muhammad by Yusuf Nâbi.
- Title (Romanized): [Tecelliyat-i Hüdaî Mahmut Efendi] Title (English): [The divine manifestations of Hüdaî Mahmut Efendi] Alternative titles: ?????? ????? ????? ?????, Date: [Late 16--]?; Manuscript number: 289; 113 leaves: paper; 206 x 150 mm. bound to 204 x 154 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with gilt decoration, fore-edge flap, and marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 65)
  Present form of the author from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 109. However, the present title is not listed in that entry.
  A treatise in Turkish verse, seemingly a translation or reworking of an original by Mahmut Hüdaî (1543 or 4-1628). Other shorter poems before and after the main title.
- Title (Romanized): Kitab-i Mürsid Uniform title: Pend-i Ahmediye kitab-i Mürsid Title (English): The guiding book Alternative titles: ???? ????, Kitab Murshid, Pend-i Ahmedi, Date: 1817; Manuscript number: 290; 249 leaves: paper; 197 x 135 mm. bound to 192 x 138 mm.; Layout: 14 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded brown leather with dark brown leather stripe over spine; torn and frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; water damage. (Box 65)
  Under the entry Ahmet Bican in the Islâm Ans?klopedisi, the present title is called Ahmediye, and its correct authorship (noted above) affirmed under the full name of Diyarbekirli Ahmet Mürsid Efendi.
  Long poem in rhyming couplets giving religio-ethical advice.
- Title (Romanized): Bizaatü'l-hükkâm fî ihkâmi'l-ahkâm Title (English): The stock of magistrates for effecting legal decisions Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ?? ????? ??????, Bizaatü'l-hükkâm fî ihkâmi'l-ahkâm, Bi?aat al-?ukkam fi i?kam al-a?kam, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 291; 172 leaves: paper; 200 x 140 mm. bound to 198 x 136 mm.; Layout: 29 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded paper on boards, with cloth stripe over spine; separating from spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage. (Box 65)
  The author calls himself Mehmet b. Mustafa b. Mahmut Istanbulî. The first surname and death dates are from Karatay, F. E. Topkap? Saray? Müzesi Kütüphanesi türkce yazmalar katalogu (318).
  Sample judicial rulings to be used as models by magistrates in composing their legal decisions.
- Title (Romanized): Gencine-i letâif Title (English): Treasury of bon mots Alternative titles: ?????? ?????, Ganjinah-i la?a'if, Date: 1574; Manuscript number: 292; 70 leaves: paper; 208 x 121 mm. bound to 206 x 123 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded paper on boards, with leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 65)
  Collection of entertaining tales dedicated (4a) to the Ottoman Sultans Selim II (15661574) and Murad III (15741595).
- Title (Romanized): [Kitap-i ravzatü'l-ulema] Title (English): [The garden of scholars] Alternative titles: [???? ??????, Raw?at al-ulama], Date: 1459 or after; Manuscript number: 293; 141 leaves: paper; 207 x 153 mm. bound to 205 x 155 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with burgundy leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 65)
  Treatise with several quotations from Koran, exegesis, and Hadith. The text also contains a number of verse tractae by someone named Arif (136b).
- Title (Romanized): Bizaatü'l-hükkâm fî ihkâmi'l-ahkâm Title (English): The stock of magistrates for effecting legal decisions Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ?? ????? ??????, Bizaatü'l-hükkâm fî ihkâmi'l-ahkâm, Bi?aat al-?ukkam fi i?kam al-a?kam, Date: [Late 17--]; Manuscript number: 294; 174 leaves: paper; 207 x 146 mm. bound to 207 x 149 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded brown leather, with burgundy leather stripe over spine, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 65)
- Title (Romanized): Nefehatü'l-üns min hazerati'l-kuds Uniform title: Nefehâtü'l-üns min hadarâti'l-kuds Title (English): Fragrances of intimacy from the presence of holy ones Alternative titles: ????? ???? ?? ????? ?????, Nafa?at al-uns min ha?arat al-quds, Date: 1609 October; Manuscript number: 295; 322 leaves: paper; 228 x 127 mm. bound to 229 x 133 mm.; Layout: 27 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with printed gilt decoration (back board only). Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated; table of contents on leaves before text. (Box 66)
  Lâmi'î's Turkish translation of an original biography of famous Sufis by Jami (1414- 1492).
- Title (Romanized): [Gülistan tercümesi] Uniform title: Gülistan tercümesi Title (English): [Translation of the Rose garden] Alternative titles: ??????, Date: 1605 June; Manuscript number: 296; 143 leaves: paper; 204 x 140 mm. bound to 202 x 139 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded brown leather, with cloth stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 66)
  Translation into Turkish of the classic work of Persian prose by Sádi.
- Title (Romanized): [Maktel-i Hüseyn] Title (English): [The murder of ?usayn] Alternative titles: ???? ???? ????, Maktel-i Imam Hüseyn, Date: [1677]?; Manuscript number: 297; 108 leaves: paper; 208 x 151 mm. bound to 207 x 153 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black leather with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; some water damage. (Box 56)
  Note on inside cover gives the date and the author. This title is indeed one of the works of Lâmi'î.
  Poem in Turkish on the martyrdom of ?usayn ibn Ali (d. 680) the grandson of the Prophet.
- Title (Romanized): Tefsir-i sure-i Fatiha Title (English): Commentary upon the Opening Chapter Alternative titles: ????? ???? ?????, Tafsir surah Fati?ah, Date: 1663 May; Manuscript number: 298; 115 leaves: paper; 204 x 147 mm. bound to 202 x 158 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black leather with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; some water damage. (Box 66)
  A Turkish translation of a commentary on the first chapter of the Koran. The manuscript contains other titles such as Vasiyet and Risale-i ücret by Birgivî Mehmet Efendi, (ca. 1522-1573), Tercüme-i mukaddeme-i Ibn el-Cezeri fi tecvid, Tercüme-i kitabi't-tecvid fî kelami'l- mecid.
- Title (Romanized): Semsiye Title (English): Solar Alternative titles: ?????, Shamsiyah, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 299; 176 leaves: paper; 206 x 137 mm. bound to 203 x 136 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage; ending missing. (Box 66)
  Author's identity from Karatay, F. E. Topkap? Saray? Müzesi Kütüphanesi türkce yazmalar katalogu (# 1623). He was the father of Yaz?c?oglu Mehmet (d. 1451), author of Muhammediye.
  Poem in Turkish on star-lore.
- Title (Romanized): Lugat-i Nimetullah Title (English): The glossary of Nímat Allah Alternative titles: ??? ???? ??, Date: 1626 April; Manuscript number: 300; 285 leaves: paper; 200 x 140 mm. bound to 197 x 135 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 66)
  Author's full name is Nimetullah b. Ahmet b. Kad? Mubarek Rumi (1b and Karatay, F. E. Topkap? Saray? Müzesi Kütüphanesi türkce yazmalar katalogu [# 2063]).
  A glossary of Persian words with Ottoman Turkish definitions.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] T?bb-? Eflâtun Title (English): [Translation of] Plato's medicine Alternative titles: ?? ??????, Date: no date; Manuscript number: 301; 170 leaves: paper; 196 x 139 mm. bound to 195 x 135 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Light brown leather with black leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 66)
  Medical treatise translated from Persian into Turkish for the Ottoman Sultan Süleyman I (the Magnificent) (15201566). Note in pencil at the foot of 1b equates this text with the Shifa' of Ibn Sina. The manuscript contains a second title.
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 302; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 67)
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i] Pend-i Attar Title (English): [Commentary on] A??ar's council Alternative titles: ??? ??? ????, Shar?-i Pand-i A??ar, Müfid, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 303; 201 leaves: paper; 209 x 129 mm. bound to 208 x 126 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, gilt inlaid, with fore-edge flap, and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 67)
  Form of author's name from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. III: 22.
  A commentary on the work of Farid al-Din A??ar (d. ca. 1230), dedicated to the Ototoman Sultan Mehmet IV (16481687).
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i Gülistan] Title (English): Commentary on the Rose Garden Alternative titles: ??? ??????, Shar?-i Gulistan, Date: 1645 September; Manuscript number: 304; 274 leaves: paper; 191 x 147 mm. bound to 193 x 151 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing at the beginning. (Box 67)
  Commentary in Turkish on the classic work of Persian prose by Sádi.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i Vikayetü'r-rivaye fi mesaili'l-hidaye]? Title (English): [Translation of the Preserving of narratives regarding the issues of guidance]? Alternative titles: ????? ??????? ?? ????? ???????, Wiqayat al-riwayah fi masa'il al-hidayah]?, Date: No date; Manuscript number: 305; 168 leaves: paper; 204 x 151 mm. bound to 203 x 147 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water and insect damage; marginalia. (Box 67)
  Connecting the author with the title using Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun under the original.
  The author gives the date 1424 and has dedicated the work to Ottoman Sultan Murad II (Murad II (14211444 and 14451451). But Kâtip Çelebi whose Kashf al-?unun has been used to identify the title writes that the author had done the translation in 1462 and dedicated to Ottoman Sultan Mehmet II (14441445, 14511481). If the same title, then this is a translation into Turkish verse of an Arabic original on religious doctrines and regulations composed by the fourteenth century al- Ma?bubi, itself being an epitome of a work by al-Marghinani (d. 1196 or 7).
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i Resehat-i aynü'l-hayat Uniform title: Resehat-i ayn el-hayat Title (English): The translation of Drops of the spring of life Alternative titles: ????? ????? ??? ??????, Rasha?at-? ayn al-?ayat, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 306; 212 leaves: paper; 221 x 158 mm. bound to 220 x 158 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green marble paper with pink paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; ending missing. (Box 67)
  This a Turkish translation of the biography of Sufi masters originally composed in Persian by ?usayn Vai? Kashifi (d. 1504 or 5). The translation is dedicated to the Ottoman Sultan Murad III (r. 1574-95). A quire containing the beginning of this title from another manuscript is laid in
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitap-i Cerrahname] Uniform title: Cerrahname Title (English): [This is the book of Surgery] Alternative titles: ????? ????, Jarrah'namah, Kitabü'l-cerrahiyei ilhaniye, Date: no date; Manuscript number: 307; 109 leaves: paper; 220 x 159 mm. bound to 210 x 158 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, bind-stamped, with faded green paste-downs, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; ending missing. (Box 67)